# LOIS ADLER-JOHNSON

(865) 964-0034 • lois.c.johnson@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/loiscjohnson

# **SUMMARY**

Public health data scientist with a unique blend of engineering, statistics, and epidemiology expertise. Applies advanced quantitative analysis skills to investigate and address health inequities across North Carolina. Promoter of open-source software and part-time baker at local grain farm.

# **EDUCATION**

**University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill** 

Master of Public Health in Applied Epidemiology

Chapel Hill, NC

Aug 2021 - May 2023

Georgia Institute of Technology

Bachelor of Science in Industrial & Systems Engineering

Concentration in Quality & Statistics

Atlanta, GA

Aug 2014 - May 2018

# **WORK & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

# North Carolina Institute for Public Health

Data Analyst & Advisor, Community Assessment & Strategy

Chapel Hill, NC Jan 2023 – Present

- Building quantitative data capacity and literacy among the public health workforce at governmental health agencies, academic institutions, and community-based organizations across North Carolina
- Providing technical assistance rooted in data equity principles for all stages of the data lifecycle, including collection, transformation, analysis, visualization, and dissemination

#### **UNC Injury Prevention Research Center**

Chapel Hill, NC

Graduate Research Assistant, NC-FASTER

Apr 2022 – Dec 2022

- Coordinated multi-institution project to improve surveillance of overdose, injury, violence prevention, and mental and behavioral health using ED visit data in NC
- Probabilistically linked NC-VDRS and NC DETECT data in R to improve firearm and suicide event surveillance
- Prepared reports and presentations on data linkage methods, results, and public health implications of our work

# UNC Gillings School of Global Public Health, Health Behavior Department

Chapel Hill, NC

Graduate Research Assistant, Young Adult Alcohol Misuse in Context

Jan 2022 - Dec 2022

- Transformed and analyzed cross-sectional survey and ecological momentary assessment (EMA) data in R and SAS
- · Led exploratory analysis of drinking motives and the use of harm reduction strategies
- Drafted academic manuscripts on the topic of young adult engagement in alcohol consumption harm reduction strategies in various physical and social contexts

# **NC DPH Injury and Violence Prevention Branch**

Raleigh, NC

Social Research Specialist, Epidemiology, Surveillance and Informatics Unit

Oct 2021 - Aug 2022

- Conducted literature review on ecological associations of violent death
- Conceptualized comprehensive statewide injury and violence surveillance Tableau dashboard
- Collected and transformed injury indicators from publicly available secondary data sources in R

# Workday, Inc.

Chicago, IL

**Functional Consultant** 

Jul 2018 – June 2021

- Architected complex global deployments of Workday Absence and Time Tracking for large enterprise organizations
- Facilitated implementation workshops for large international audiences in NA, LATAM, EMEA, and APAC regions
- Used product knowledge to develop, configure, and test strategic solutions that meet customers' global needs

#### CDC Division of HIV/AIDS Prevention

Atlanta, GA

Team Lead for Senior Capstone

Aug 2017 - May 2018

- Developed user-friendly web-based resource allocation modeling tool to facilitate data-driven HIV funding decisions
- Built robust optimization model in R and Excel with cost, efficacy, budget, population, and uncertainty parameters

#### The White House

Washington, D.C.

Operations Intern, Obama Administration

Aug 2016 - Dec 2016

- Improved fulfillment efficiency for miscellaneous requests across the White House campus using original process maps
- Triaged operations requests and oversaw logistics of 27 conference rooms for all White House staff and guests

#### **VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE**

### **Birth Partners at UNC Medical Center**

Chapel Hill, NC

Volunteer Doula

Jan 2022 - Jan 2023

Provided emotional, informational, and physical support to birthing persons before, during, and after childbirth

**UN Women USA Chicago** 

Chicago, IL Mar 2020 – Aug 2021

Director of Development

Mar 20

• Spearheaded fundraising campaigns and events that raised over \$15,000, tripling the previous year's total

Motivated 250+ individual donors to support global UN Women initiatives (e.g., ending violence against women)

Public Affairs Committee Jan 2019 – Aug 2021

Assembled a collaborative community of organizations in Chicago dedicated to advancing the rights of women and girls

**Field Museum**Guest Relations Volunteer, Docent

Chicago, IL Feb 2019 – Jul 2021

- Provided a positive experience for visitors through greetings, exhibit recommendations, and problem resolution
- · Educated visitors on Ancient Egypt, Botany, and the museum's worldwide conservation efforts through exhibit tours

# **SKILLS & AWARDS**

Programming & Software: R, R Shiny, Quarto, Python, ArcGIS, SAS, Stata, SQL, Tableau, Excel, HTML/CSS, Canva

**Awards**: UNC Gillings School of Public Health Travel Award (2022), Workday Living Our Values Award (2020), National Alpha Kappa Psi Outstanding Leader Award for Unity (2018), Georgia Tech Industrial & Systems Engineering Ambassador of Year (2017), Georgia Tech Federal Jackets Fellowship (2016)

#### **PUBLICATIONS & PRESENTATIONS**

### **Peer-Reviewed Published Manuscripts**

Cox, M. J., **Johnson, L.**, Roudebush, M., Godbole, A., Egan, K. L. (2024). Likelihood of engagement in protective behavioral strategies by young adults across physical and social contexts: implications for adaptive interventions. *Substance Use and Misuse*. https://doi.org/10.1080/10826084.2024.2310484. [PMID: 38308201]

Roudebush, M., Godbole, A., **Johnson, L.**, Egan, K. L., & Cox, M. J. (2023). Alcohol protective behavioral strategies for young adults: a content analysis across drinking contexts and gender. *The American Journal of Drug and Alcohol Abuse*. https://doi.org/10.1080/00952990.2023.2272035. [PMID: 38011681]

Waller, A., Harmon, K. J., Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, (2023). Emergency Department Visits Prior to Firearm Death: The NC LEADS Project. *North Carolina Medical Journal*. https://doi.org/10.18043/001c.81274. [PMID: 39302307]

Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., & Harmon, K. J. (2023). Feasibility of linking violent death decedents to prior-month emergency department visits in North Carolina, 2019-2020. *Injury Prevention*. https://doi.org/10.1136/ip-2022-044821. [PMID: 37094916]

Peer-Reviewed Presentations (Completed or Accepted for Presentation via Competitive Review)

Wallace, J., **Adler-Johnson**, L., Jones, L., James, D., Davis, B. (October 2024). Stepping back: Building equity in academic collaborations and technical assistance. Oral presentation at the American Public Health Association Annual Meeting. Minneapolis, MN.

**Adler-Johnson**, L. (July 2024). Using R to Co-Create an Inclusive Data Analysis Approach with the HBCU Health Equity Data Consortium. Oral presentation at the useR! Annual Conference. Salzburg, Austria.

**Johnson, L. C.**, Neuroth, L. M., Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., Harmon, K. J. (April 2023). Novel application of a data linkage framework NC-VDRS suicide deaths, 2019-2020. Poster presentation at the Society for Advancement of Violence and Injury Research Annual Conference. Denver, CO.

Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., Harmon, K. J. (April 2023). Applying a probabilistic data linkage approach to identify prior-year emergency department visits among violent death decedents in North Carolina, 2019-2020. Poster presentation at the Society for Advancement of Violence and Injury Research Annual Conference. Denver, CO.

#### **Published Reports and Blogs**

Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E. (2022). *Linking North Carolina Violent Death Reporting System and NC DETECT Emergency Department Visit Data for Firearm Deaths: A Preliminary Report*. NC DETECT, Carolina Center for Health Informatics, Department of Emergency Medicine Injury Prevention Research Center. https://ncdetect.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/13428/2022/09/LEADS REPORT NC 9.14.22 FINAL.pdf

**Lois Johnson**, "Investigating Emergency Department Utilization in the Year Prior to Firearm Death in NC", *NC DETECT* (blog), December 14, 2022, https://ncdetect.org/2022/12/investigating-emergency-department-utilization-in-the-year-prior-to-firearm-death-in-nc/.